Dear  Oreki Houtarou,
折木奉太郎殿
I am currently writing to you from Benares.
前略
私は今ベナレスにいます
Although late, please accept my congratulations for passing your entrance exams.
ちょっと遅れたけど 合格おめてどう
As I understand, you decided upon Kamiyama High.
結局神山高校だってね
Now that you have begun high school,
無事高校生になったあんたに姉として一つアドバイスしてあげる
let me give you one piece of advice as your sister.
Join the Classics Club!
古典部に入りなさい
It has a long-running history,
伝統ある部活よ
and I too was a member during my high school days.
そして私が所属していた部でもある
I have heard that the club currently has no members remaining.
聞いた話だと わが古典部の部員は現在ゼロ
As nobody has joined this year, they plan to to disband it.
今年入部者がいなければ消滅するそうなの
As an alumnus of the club, I cannot allow that to happen.
古典部OGとしてそれはあまりに忍びないわ
Houtarou,
奉太郎
please protect the stage of your sister's youth, the Classics Club.
姉の青春の場 古典部を守りなさい
All you need to do is sign up for the club.
名前を置いておくだけでいいから
It's not like you have anything better to do, right?
どうせやりたいことなんかないでしょ
Yours sincerely,
かしこ 折木共恵
Oreki Tomoe.
Bored, sitting on the windowsill,
退屈な窓辺に吹き込む風に
I frown at the wind to hide my awkwardness
顔を顰めたのは照れくさ　その裏返し
Hyouka
KamiGami
@ 湮·Molly／小然·酸菜／喵儿·小冷／时末·竭力而为
I nod uncertainly as I shape
曖昧に頷く掌の今日
the future in my hands feeling mighty
描いてる自分は少し大袈裟で
I feel that the wind is bringing change
何かが変わりそうな気がしているよ
心に呼びかける君のせいだね
I guess that's your fault for calling out to my heart
The cloudy sky tells a tale of what's to come
曇り空覗いた予感
Spread our wings with more courage than ever before
手を伸ばそう　いつよりも力強い勇気で
光も影もまだ遠くで
Light and dark are still vague in the distance
but still we want to know the reason behind kindness
それでも僕らは優しさの理由が知りたい
No one so far has ever reached
今は誰の名前でもない
the shining distance far beyond
輝きの彼方へ
Let's get there before the past takes it all
全部過去になる前に見つけに行こう
One, two, three, four!
Five, six, seven, eight!
古典部が復活してから一ヶ月
It's been one month since the revival of the Classics Club.
Activities of the esteemed Classics Club
享有盛名的古籍研究社之活动
Earth Sci. Prep. room
ここ地学準備室は俺の中で（こんにちは）
It ended up being much easier to visit the clubroom than I expected.
Good afternoon!
思ったより気安い場所となっていた（よう）
Hi.
放課後に退屈を感じれば そこを訪れる
Whenever I'm bored after classes, I just drop by.
どうぞ
Have some.
家の頂き物です 好きに摘まんでください
I brought them from home.
Take whichever you'd like.
サンキュー
Thanks.
一緒にいて 疲れないのであれば 俺はもともと人嫌いというわけではない
As long as it's not too tiring,
I don't mind being around others. I'm not antisocial.
不毛です
This is a waste of time.
一年に二回植えるやつか
Doesn't that mean you'll save nine?
それは二毛作です
轮植：同一块耕地，一年种植两次不同作物，收成两次的作法。
That's a stitch in time.
ひょっとして駄洒落ですか
Was that a pun?
聞くな
Don't ask that.
That's not the point!
いえ そうじゃなくてですね
不毛なのか
Is it a waste of time?
そうです 不毛です
Yes! A waste!
What is?
何が
この放課後がです
This whole afternoon!
目的無き日々は生産的じゃありません
We can't be productive if we have no purpose!
お説ごもっとも で
Thank you for those words of wisdom.
Then, is there something else you expect to get out of the Classics Club?
お前は何かこの古典部に求めるものがあるとでも
あります
Yes, there is.
Oh?
It's a personal thing.
でも それは一身上の都合です
I've heard that before.
前にも聞いたぞ
今は古典部のことを言ってるんです
But right now, I'm talking about the club itself.
部活動ですから活動をしなければいけません
A club without club activities is no club at all!
目的がない
We have no purpose.
いえ あります
Actually, we do.
十月の文化祭に 文集を出します
We're going to release an anthology at the culture fair in October!
文集
An anthology?
はい
Yes!
Give it up.
止めよう 手間が掛かりすぎる
That'd take way too much effort.
No! Nothing less than an anthology will do!
いいえ 文集でないとだめなんです
文学祭に一枚噛みたいなら ほかにも方法があるだろう
If you want to take part in the culture fair so badly, can't we do something easier?
模擬店とか
Like a food stall?
神高文化祭は伝統的に模擬店禁止だそうです
Traditionally, those kinds of stalls aren't allowed at Kami High's culture fair.
それに 文集のための予算は出てますし 顧問の先生からも頼まれています
I already submitted the costings for the anthology,
and our club advisor asked me to do it as well.
また 文集は四十年以上の伝統があるので 途絶えさせたくないそうです
The Classics Club anthology is a 40-year-old tradition,
so they don't want us to just let it die.
そういう事情があるなら 先に言え
Couldn't you have mentioned all this earlier?
I get it. I'll help.
分かった やるよ
Thanks!
はい
それで　その文集ってのはどんな内容なんだ
What's this anthology supposed to consist of, anyway?
分かりません
I don't know!
おいおい
Come on.
すみません これから調べればいいと思ってました
Sorry. I figured we could work that out later.
とにかく バックナンバーがあれば取っ掛かりはつかめると思います
If we can find one from a previous year, that might be a good starting point.
探してみましょう
Let's take a look around!
ないな
Nothing here.
じゃ 図書室でしょうか
Then let's check the library!
行ってみましょう
Let's go!
何してるんですか 折木さんも行くんです ほら
What's the matter? You're coming too.
Come on.
気が進まん 今日は金曜だから 図書当番はたぶん
I'd rather not.
It's Friday, so the library assistant will be—
Library
あれ 折木じゃない 久しぶりね 会いたくなかったわ
Oh? Oreki, huh?
Long time no see. Pity it couldn't stay that way.
よー 伊原 会いに来てやったぜ
Hey, Ibara. I thought I'd drop by to say "hi".
ここは共用の聖域よ あんたには似合わないんじゃない
This is a sanctuary of culture.
Not your kind of place.
なら 自分にはお似合いだってのか ご立派なことで
But I bet it fits you perfectly, Your Highness.
相っ変わらず最低ね 冷やかしに来たなら 帰りなさいよ
You're as annoying as ever.
If you just came here to bother me, go away.
ええと
Um...
や 奉太郎 奇遇だね
Hey, Houtarou!
What a coincidence!
相変わらず仲がいいじゃないか
I see you two are still getting along well.
さすがは鏑屋中ベストカップル
Living up to your name as Kaburaya Junior High's best couple, huh?
ふざけんな
Can it.
こんな陰気な男 なめくじのほうがまだマシよ
He's such a drag.
A slug would be more fun to be around.
なめくじ
A... slug?
大体福ちゃん
Anyway, Fuku, you've sure got guts to tell me that, knowing how I feel and all.
私の気持ちを知っててよくそんな冗談が言えるわね
ああ ごめんね摩耶花 傷ついちゃった
Sorry, sorry. Didn't mean to reopen old wounds.
またそうやって冗談めかしてごまかすんだから
You're letting your jokes get the better of you again.
ほんといい加減にしてよね
You really oughta quit messing around.
Um, what's going on between those two?
どういうご関係なんですか
中学の頃から里志に惚れてるんだ
She's had a crush on him since junior high.
Oh!
千反田さん こちらは伊原摩耶花 僕らと同じ鏑屋中出身だ
Chitanda, this is Ibara Mayaka.
She went to the same junior high as us.
よろしく
Nice to meet you.
麻耶花 こちらは千反田えるさん 僕がこないだ入部した古典部の部長だよ
Mayaka, this is Chitanda Eru.
She's from the Classics Club I just joined.
こちらこそ よろしくお願いします
Nice to meet you too.
それより 二人揃って何の用だい
By the way, what brings you two here?
Oh, right!
そうでした あの 伊原さん お聞きしたいことがあるんですが
Ibara, there was something I wanted to ask about.
はい
Go on...
ここに部活の文集って置いてありますか 古典部のなんですけど
Do you keep the previous anthologies published by the club here?
The Classics Club, that is.
古典部 なかったと思うけど
The Classics Club...
I don't think we do...
If they're not on the shelves, they might be in the archives...
表にないなら 書庫かしら
そうですか
I see.
何で文集を
What do you need them for?
文化祭で文集を作ることになったので
We're making a new anthology for the culture fair,
一度以前の文集を見ておこうと思いまして
so we thought we'd better take a look at the previous ones.
へええ 「カンヤ祭」に出品するんだ
Oh, you're doing something for the Kan'ya Fair?
奉太郎がよく承知したね
I'm surprised Houtarou agreed.
ほんとんど事後承諾だったけどな
It kinda happened after the fact.
What's the "Kan'ya Fair"?
「カンヤ祭」
聞いたことない 神高文化祭の俗称だよ
You haven't heard of it?
It's what everyone calls Kamiyama High's culture fair.
またお前の考えた俗称じゃないだろうな
This isn't another of your tall tales, is it?
本当さ 手芸部の先輩は皆「カンヤ祭」って呼んでるよ
It's true! My seniors in the Handicraft Club all call it that.
摩耶花は
And you, Mayaka?
We call it that in the Book Club too.
「漫研」でも「カンヤ祭」って言ってるわ
カンヤ どういう字を書くんですか
"Kan'ya"...
How do you write that?
I don't know... though I asked around.
分からないんだ 聞いて回ったりはしたんだけどね
It probably started off as the "Kamiyama High School Culture Fair",
まあ たぶん神山高校文化祭が神山祭になって
then became the "Kamiyama Culture Fair",
then the "Kan'yama Fair" and finally the "Kan'ya Fair", I guess.
カンヤマ祭 カンヤ祭ってところかと思ってるんだけど
それで 千反田さん 文集は書庫を探せばあるかもしれけど
So, Chitanda,
we might be able to find them if we take a look in the archives,
but the librarian is at a staff meeting right now, so we can't go in.
ちょっと司書の先生が会議で席を外してるから今入れないのよ
後三十分もすれば戻ってくると思うけど
She'll be back in about half an hour, I think.
待つ
Want to wait?
どうします
What should we do?
待つか
I guess we could wait.
あんたは帰ってもいいのに
You might as well go home.
へーいへい
Yeah, yeah.
待って 奉太郎
Wait, Houtarou!
摩耶花 さっきの話二人にも聞いてもらったらどうだい
Mayaka, why don't you tell them that story?
ええ
そうね 折木 たまには頭を働かせてみる気はない
I guess.
Oreki,
feel like putting your brain to work for once?
Nope.
ない
どういうお話ですか
What are you talking about?
愛なき愛読書の話さ
The popular but unwanted book.
愛なき愛読書
The popular but unwanted book?
何とも奇妙な話でね
It's a pretty weird story.
どう考えても辻褄が合わなくて 麻耶花と首を捻ったところなんだ
No matter how hard we thought, it never made any sense.
Mayaka and I were out of ideas.
Please tell us!
ぜひ聞かせてください
私が当番で金曜放課後ここに来るとね
Every Friday, I'm here working as the assistant librarian.
毎週同じ本が返却されてるのよ
And every Friday I see the same book in the returns tray.
For five weeks in a row.
今日で五週連続
これだけでも変な話でしょ
That's weird enough on its own, right?
This is the book.
これがその本
きれいな本
It's so pretty!
It's huge.
kamiyama high school:
fifty years of history
でかい
ちょっと中を見てもいいですか
Can I take a peek inside?
どうぞ
Go on.
折木さんも ほら
You too, Oreki.
普通の学校史ですね
It's just your typical school history book.
これを読むのはかなり大変そうですね
This doesn't look like an easy read.
これは毎週借りるやつがいても おかしくはないな
It wouldn't be that unusual for someone to borrow this every week, right?
You've never borrowed a book from here, have you?
あんた ここで本借りたことないでしょ
うちの図書室の貸出期間は二週間なの
You can borrow books for up to two weeks.
だから毎週借りる必要はないのよ
So you wouldn't need to keep borrowing the same book every week.
なのに この本は毎週返却されるんだってさ
And yet, this book gets returned every week.
誰が借りたかは分かるんですか
Do you know who keeps borrowing it?
もちろん 裏に貸出リストがあるから 見てみて
Of course.
The list of borrowers is at the back. Take a look.
あれ 折木さん 見てください
Take a look at this, Oreki!
Class
Name
Borrowed
Suzuki Yoshie
Shima Saori
Yamaguchi
Ryouko
Sawakiguchi Misaki
Machita
Kyouko
毎週違う人が借りてます しかも全員その日のうちに返してます
A different person borrows it every week! And they all return it on the same day!
Replay
IV. XX, 15:40
IV. XX, 12:21
Yeah.
そうなのよ 貸出と返却が同じ日で五周連続
They all borrowed and returned it on the same day, for five weeks in a row.
時間も分かってて
We also know when it was borrowed.
They always borrow it during lunch break and return it after school.
五人とも昼休みに借りて放課後に返してるの
どうだい 気になるだろ
What do you think?
Caught your interest?
ええ 私 気になります
Yes...
I can't stop thinking about it!
kamiyama high school:
fifty years of history
ちょっと考えてみましょうよ 折木さん
Just consider it for a moment, Oreki!
Damn you, Satoshi.
おのれ里志
What do you think?
こうなることを見越して呼び止めたな
Pretty interesting, right?
You knew this would happen.
折木さんは 鍵のこととか秘密クラブとかあんなに見事にといてくれたじゃないですか
You figured out the story behind the locked door and the secret club so easily too!
What are you talking about?
何 それ
Just an interesting side of Houtarou that you may not have heard about.
奉太郎の興味深い一面に纏わる話さ
止めろ 人聞きの悪い
Cut it out. It sounds bad when you say it like that.
とにかく 気になるんです
Anyway, I can't stop thinking about it!
ならん
I can.
なるんです
I can't!
ならん
I can!
折木 静かに
Oreki!
Quiet.
千反田さんも
You too, Chitanda.
Sorry.
はい
うかつだった
I was careless.
これ以上の拒絶や言い逃れはむしろエネルギー効率が悪い
Trying to say no at this point would cost me significantly more energy.
Then...
ならば
そうだな 少し考えてみるか
I guess. Let's mull it over for a minute.
はい
Thanks!
福ちゃん 折木って頭良かったっけ
Fuku, was Oreki actually smart all along?
Not really.
あんまり でもこういう役に立たないことだと 時々役に立つんだ
But with pointless stuff like this,
every now and then he's not entirely useless.
お前ら 言いたい放題だな
You can shut up now.
立夏
立夏 夏立为因
Summer begins
And thus, summer has begun.
Hyouka
kamiyama high school:
fifty years of history
For five weeks in a row, different people have borrowed this book,
五週間連続で別の人間がこの本を借り その日のうちに返す
and returned it on the same day.
これを偶然だと言い張るのは簡単だが
It would be easy to say it's a coincidence,
but Chitanda wouldn't accept that.
千反田は納得しないだろ
大事なのは真実ではない 千反田が納得することなのだ
It doesn't have to be true.
It just has to be something Chitanda can accept.
Let's see.
さて 昼休みに借りて放課後に返していては
Book
Lunch break
Library
Assistant
If they borrow it during lunch break and return after classes,
Book
they wouldn't have much time to read it.
とてもこれを読む暇などなかろうし
Lunch break
break
plus
equals
65 Minutes
Insufficient
School
Home
If they didn't plan to take it home with them,
家に持ち帰らないなら 借りずに図書室で読めばいい
No
they could have just read it in the library instead.
kamiyama high school:
fifty years of history
Conclusion:
結論
They didn't borrow the book because they wanted to read it.
この本は図書の本分を果たすために使用されているのではない
とすると
Which means...
本を 読む以外に使うとしたら どう使う
What can you do with a book besides reading it?
You could put a few books together to use as a pillow.
何冊か積めば枕にいいかも
腕に使えば盾になるね
You could tie it to your arm and use it as a shield.
Put some effort into it!
もっとまじめに考えてくれ
そうですよ こういう本ならではの使う道があるはずです
That's right! There has to be some purpose that only this book could be used for.
Then what do you think, Chitanda?
じゃ 千反田さんはどう思う
That's right...
そうですね 重ねれば浅漬けが漬かります
You could use it to flatten vegetables for pickling!
お前らにはもう聞かない
Forget I asked.
What kind of honor roll did she manage to end up on?
千反田って 本当に成績優秀なのか
The local district's "Top Airheads"?
ただの天然にしか思えんのだが
視点を変えよう
Let's look at this from another angle.
Suzuki  Yoshie
Shima  Saori
Yamaguchi  Ryouko
Sawakiguchi  Misaki
Machita  Kyouko
毎週別の人間が借りているのはどういうわけか
What can we conclude from the fact that someone different borrows it each week?
Looking at their names, they're all girls.
名前から見て 全員女だな
I can think of two possibilities.
考えられるのは二つ
Suzuki Yoshie
Someone
Yamaguchi Ryouko
Sawakiguchi Misaki
Someone
Machita Kyouko
Shima Saori
Someone
彼女らに共通点はないが
First, that they have nothing in common,
この本を金曜日の午後に使うことが流行っている場合
and this book is just popular on Friday afternoons.
Or that they use the book as a group,
そして 彼女らはグループでこの本を使用し
Machita
Kyouko
Sawakiguchi Misaki
Tori Saori
Suzuki Yoshie
Yamaguchi
Ryouko
当番制で順番に借りて使っている場合だ
and borrow it in turns.
No group         Group
流行りねえ
Popular, huh?
占いとか
How about for fortune-telling?
Like this?
こんな感じ？
今週のあなたのラッキーアイテムは学校史
"Your lucky item this week is... the school history book!
金曜日の午後に借りて その日のうちに返すと
If you borrow it Friday afternoon and return it the same day,
everything will go well with your boyfriend!"
彼氏とうまくいくかも なんて
Just kidding.
Don't be stupid. And remember, this happened five weeks in a row!
馬鹿馬鹿しい それに五週連続だぞ
Don't mind me.
言ってみただけだよ
共通点は全員が女 それと二年生 クラスは違う
Here's what they have in common: They're all second-year girls.
Different classes, though.
I wonder if there's a reason they're all girls?
みんな女なのは 何か理由があるのかしら
Hard to say.
なんとも言えんな
If you randomly selected five students from this school,
全校から無作為に五人選んで
それが全員女である可能性は十分ある
there's a decent chance they'll all be girls.
Girls like to stick together too.
それと 同性で群れるのも珍しいことじゃないよね
何かの合図ってのはどうだ？
Could it be some kind of secret message?
Like returning it one way up to say you passed, and the other way up to say you failed.
たとえば 本を表にして返してあったら「可」
裏なら「不可」とか
I don't think they could use it as a message in that way.
表裏で合図ってのはないと思うわよ
Look.
ほら
なるほど これじゃ表も裏もわからないね
I see.
You can't really tell which way up they are.
Well, I guess no matter how much Oreki thinks about it, that's as far as he can go.
まあ 折木がいくら知恵を絞ってもそんなところよ
Fuku spent ages thinking about it as... well...
私と福ちゃんだって 散々考えたんだか…ら
What?
何？
何かにおいがします
It smells.
Really?
そう？
I don't smell anything.
何もにおわないけど？
No, it does.
いいえ 確かに
It's quite pungent.
何かの刺激臭です シンナーのような
Like paint thinner...
Now I'm certain!
間違えありません
Like a dog...
犬
Well, if Chitanda is so certain about it,
まあ でも千反田さんがこうまで断言するなら 勘違いじゃなさそうだね
I don't think she could be mistaken.
とすれば
Which means...
奉太郎 その顔は何かわかったね
Houtarou, your face says you figured something out.
Really?
本当に？
Kind of. I can't be certain, though.
まあな 確定は出来んが
Chitanda, how about a bit of exercise?
千反田 運動する気はないか 行ってほしいところがあるんだが
There's this place I'd like you to go.
I got it!
わかりました
No, I'm not going. Just you.
いや… 俺は行かずにお前だけで
Just me?
私だけ？ どうしてですか
Why?
それは…
Well...
You're right, Chitanda!
そのとおりだよ 千反田さん
Don't let him just make you run around!
奉太郎に使われるなんて あっちゃいけない
He can only be useful if someone uses him!
奉太郎は使ってこそ 役に立つんだから
You really don't know when to shut up.
随分な言い草だな
No, I just thought that if I needed to go somewhere you'd want come along.
いえ 私はどこかに行くなら一緒かと思っただけです
Oh, I see.
おお なるほどね
では 行きましょうか 折木さん
So let's go, Oreki.
Welcome!
いらっしゃいませ ようこそ当店へ
Thank you for honoring our restaurant.
We have prepared two menus for you.
二つのコース料理をご用意しております どちらにいたしますか
Dull course
Vegetable Bites of Escapism
Terrine of Idleness and Lethargy
Armchair Meunière with Low Energy Sauce
Penne hardened with Lies, Golden Web style
Slowly stewed Status Quo, Mistake style
Tiramisu of Rejection and Peace
Colorful Course
Vegetable Bites of Danger
Sautè of Trouble and Effort
Tagliatelle of Wasted Effort
Trofie of Interest with Worthwhile Sauce
Provence style Curiosity roast
and Well Done Mille-feuille
Which one would you like?
The chef's suggestion is this one.
お勧めはこちらですよ
Oreki?
折木さん？
わかったよ
I get it, I get it.
今日は雨で体育が潰れたからな
PE class had to be called off today due to rain,
so I still have some energy left.
可処分エネルギーはまだ残ってる
はい
Okay!
どんだけ限られたエネルギーなのよ あんたは…
Just how limited is your energy to begin with?
Drop it.
ほっとけ じゃ 行くか
Let's go then.
はい
Okay.
Wait!
待って 私も行く
I'm going too.
I'm a bit interested.
ちょっと気になるし
福ちゃん ちょっと留守番お願いね
Fuku, can you take the counter for a while?
I can't just leave when I'm supposed to be minding the library.
だって 図書当番放り出しておけないでしょう？
See you, Satoshi.
じゃあな 里志
留守番 よろしく
Hold the fort while we're gone.
それで 折木さん どこへ行くんですか
So where are we going, Oreki?
The art room.
美術室だ
That's in the other building.
向こうの校舎ね
Yeah. It's pretty far.
そう 遠い だから行きたくなかったんだ
That's why I didn't want to go.
Is there any limit to your laziness?
あんた ほんっっとうに物臭ね
そのに何が？
So what's in the art room?
その前に整理だ
Firstly, let's organize our information.
Consider what they would use the book for.
あの本の使い道だが
First of all, I doubt there are any girls who would use that huge book during their break.
休み時間にあんなでかい物を使う女子はまずいないだろう
Which means they must use it in class.
となれば 考えられるのは授業だ
Considering that they're in the same year but different classes, what subjects could it be?
学年が同じでクラスが別の生徒が関係する授業といえば 何だ？
体育か芸術科目ですね
PE or arts classes, right?
Yeah.
そう あの五人は毎週授業の前に当番を決めて借りに来てたんだ
The five girls took turns borrowing the book before class every week.
But we don't know if it's every week.
毎週ってのがわからないわね
Since books can be borrowed for up to two weeks...
貸し出し期間は二週間だから
It's so huge, it'd be easier to just borrow it again each week than to take it home with you.
あんなでかい本 持っておくより毎週返しておく方が楽だろ？
I guess.
ああ そうね
What's wrong?
どうしたの？
Something smells like the book!
本と同じにおいがします
Really?
本当に？
中を見ればわかる
Look inside and you'll understand.
本の使い道はあれだ
That's what they use the book for.
二年D E F組の合同授業
Classes 2-D, 2-E and 2-F take Art together,
and they would have painted those pictures.
芸術科目美術課で製作された絵
The book's cover makes it perfect as a model.
あの想定なら 絵のモチーフにぴったりだ
So that smell was paint!
絵の具のにおいだったんですね
How did you figure it out?
どうしてわかったの？
I just...
どうしてって…
I just had a moment of inspiration.
ただのひらめき ただの運だろ
It was just luck.
Library
いやあ 見事見事
Ah, well done, well done!
I never would have thought they'd use it as a model for painting.
さすがに絵のモチーフに使ったなんて 想像もつかなかったよ
How'd you manage to figure it out?
なんであんなのがわかるの？
You're weird, Oreki.
折木 変
What are you saying?
何を言う 俺ほど平均的な人間はいない
I'm as average as they come.
I do wonder about that.
さて どうだろうね
But you really did surprise me, Oreki.
でも 本当に折木さんには驚かされました
I'm really interested in what goes on inside your head.
折木さんの頭の中には私も興味あります
Interested?
興味が？
Yes.
ええ 一度切り開いて中を見てみたいくらいです
So much I'd like to cut it open to see.
There's nothing unusual about my brain.
たいした脳味噌じゃないぞ
A top-ranking student like yourself wouldn't get anything out of it.
学業優秀なお前が見ても 得るものはない
Huh? She's that good?
へえ 学業優秀なの
Yeah!
そうそう 中間テストはまだだけど
The midterms are still a while away,
but I'm sure she'll be among the best in our year!
きっと学年でもトップクラスの成績をとるよ
No,
いえ いくら成績がとれても それはパーツの集合体にすぎません
even if I get good grades,
I'm just putting together things I already know.
What I want to know is beyond those things.
私はそういうパーツではなく 思考を生み出すシステムが知りたいんです
I want to understand the system that gives birth to thoughts.
O-kay...
はあ…
Actually, her sense of smell is even more of a mystery to me.
というか こいつの嗅覚の方が俺にはよほど謎なんだが
Maybe Oreki could...
折木さんなら もしかしたら
ん？
あ いえ なんでも
Nothing.
Never mind.
Well, I guess that was pretty fun.
まあ とにかく なかなか面白い時間を過ごさせてもらったよ
千反田さんは？
What about you, Chitanda?
Of course! It was loads of fun!
勿論楽しかったです 時間を短く感じました
But it was all over so quickly!
I spent hours on it and never figured it out...
私は何時間かかってもわからなかったのに
That's so frustrating!
悔しい
That's why I said he can be useful at times.
だから言ったじゃないか 時々役立つって
でも 折木に負けるのは納得いかない
But I hate being outdone by Oreki!
やっぱり悔しい
It's really, really frustrating!
Now, chill out.
まあまあ 摩耶花 落ち着いて
違う ここが違う
This isn't it.
This just isn't it.
こんな風に俺はならない
This isn't how I am.
何が違う 何が
What's different?
What?
That's right, I guess...
そうなんだよねえ
極稀にひらめく一瞬の輝きか はたまた…
That rare flash of sparkling brilliance...
Oreki, you can't leave yet!
折木さん 帰っちゃだめです
Why?
なんで？ ああ 文集
Oh. The anthology.
That's right. We need to wait for the librarian.
そうです 先生を待たないと
Sometimes, Houtarou acts like he's not all there.
奉太郎って 時々抜けてるんだよね
Sometimes?
時々？過大評価じゃない～
That's an understatement.
Ibara, thanks for your help.
伊原さん ご苦労さま もう帰っていいわよ
That's all for today.
Ah, you're back, Ms. Itoigawa.
はい 戻ってたんですか 糸魚川先生
先生 古典部の福部里志です
I'm Fukube Satoshi from the Classics Club.
We're looking for an old edition of the anthology to refer to when making the new one.
文集を作るためにバックナンバーを探しているんですが
Can we take a look in the archives?
書庫を調べてもいいですか
古典部 文集？
The Classics Club's...
anthology?
あなたたち 古典部なの そう
You're in the Classics Club? I see.
I'm sorry, but we don't have any of the previous anthologies in the archive.
残念だけど 文集のバックナンバーは書庫にはないわ
Could you have overlooked it?
見落としということは？
I don't think so. If we had it, I'd know.
あったら さすがに覚えてるわ
Excuse me.
じゃ 失礼するわね
はあ… すいませんでした
Sorry for the trouble.
I guess that's it, Chitanda.
だそうだよ 千反田さん
This is bad news.
これは困りました
We'll find it, I'm sure.
そのうち見つかるさ
How was it, Oreki?
折木 どう？
Do you feel refreshed from having solved that mystery?
問題解いて気分はすっきりってとこかしら
別に
Not really.
Oh.
あっそ
There's nothing we can do about it. Let's go home.
仕方ありません 帰りましょう
We still had a good harvest today.
今日は収穫もありましたし
What do you mean?
なんだ？ それ
It's a personal thing.
いえ 一身上の都合です
またそれか
That again?
そう 折木さんなら もしかしたら
Yeah.
Maybe Oreki could...
Hello? Oreki speaking.
はい 折木です
もしもし 千 千反田です
Hello? It's Chitanda.
千反田？
Chitanda?
Sorry, were you resting?
あの すみません もしかしてお休みでしたか
I guess.
まあな 姉貴の電話かと思った
I thought it was my sister calling.
So? How come you're calling on a Sunday?
で 日曜なんかにどうした？
Sorry to bother you,
すみません できれば 今日お会いしたいんですけど
but I'd like to meet you today.
Pine
apple
Sand
I'd like to ask a very special favor of you.
折木さんに折り入ってお話したいことがあるんです
遅い
She's late.
I'm sorry for calling you out like this.
お呼びたてして すみません
So? What's all this about?
それで 何か用だったか
Huh?
はい？
I'm asking why you had me come all the way here.
何のためにこの店まで呼び出したのかって聞いてるんだ
このお店を指定したのは折木さんです
You're the one who chose this café.
I'm going home.
帰る
Please wait!
ま 待ってください
My Sundays are important to me, okay?
貴重な日曜日だぞ お前と漫才するために浪費など出来ん
I'm not going to waste my time on this comedy act!
I'm sorry...
す すみません
私緊張してるんです
I'm so nervous.
Nervous, huh?
緊張ねえ
Were you planning to confess to me or something?
俺に告白でも… するつもりか
You might consider it a confession.
告白といえば そうかもしれません
Let us meet in a blissful dream tonight, let it be our love
今夜恋に変わる　幸せな夢で会おう
Find me, I beg you
きっと　ねぇ見つけてね
We promised to meet, drifting in and out of sleep
まどろみの約束
This sprouting warmth confuses us
芽生えてた温もり　暖かくて戸惑う
Don't you understand this feeling yet?
こんな気持ちをまだ　あなたは分からないよ
Normally such random glances hold no meaning
そんな視線には意味なんて　別にないはず
Isn't it the same when making friends?
だって友達にしてるのと同じ
The little shooting stars we wish upon, vanishing into the dawn
明け方に消えてく　小さな願星
are a magic that only unfolds in the night
夜の間だけの魔法を…
Let us meet in a blissful dream tonight, let it be our love
今夜恋に変わる　幸せな夢で会おう
Find me, I beg you
きっと　ねぇ見つけてね
We promised to meet, drifting in and out of sleep
まどろみの約束
次回 事情ある古典部の末裔
Next time: Inheritors of the Classics Club and its circumstances.
Inheritors of the Classics club and its circumstances